<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Unto the right honourable, the Lords of his Majesty's Privy Council. The petition of the Earl of Seafort.</title>
            <author>Seaforth, Kenneth Mackenzie, Earl of, d. 1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2170C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183642</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52615098</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52615098</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05758)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2762:65)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Unto the right honourable, the Lords of his Majesty's Privy Council. The petition of the Earl of Seafort.</title>
                  <author>Seaforth, Kenneth Mackenzie, Earl of, d. 1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: Creased, print show through with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Resisting an officer --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:176122:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Unto the Right Honourable, The Lords of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Privy Council.</head>
            <head>The Petition of the Earl of SEAFORT</head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>THat where your Lordſhips have been pleaſed to find the <hi>Deforcement</hi> and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot Lybelled at the Inſtance of <hi>Pitliver</hi> and <hi>Tulloch</hi> proven; and have decern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, as I am informed, in a <hi>very great Sum.</hi> I do with all reſpect to your Lordſhips, beſeech the following Reaſons may be conſidered, for clearing that I cannot be lyable on either of theſe Accompts.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> as to the <hi>Deforcement,</hi> I do with ſubmiſſion contend there was none: For there can be no <hi>Deforcement,</hi> where there is no <hi>Meſſenger:</hi> And <hi>Robert Dallas</hi> alledged to have been Deforced, was no Meſſenger. And I did produce an <hi>Atteſtation</hi> from the <hi>Lyon,</hi> for clearing that he was <hi>deprived;</hi> and his deprivation Intimat but a few Weeks before his pretended Deforcement.</p>
            <p>I know it was urged, 1<hi>mo.</hi> That he was <hi>Habite and Repute</hi> Meſſenger. 2<hi>do.</hi> That he was deprived only upon a <hi>Formality</hi> by the <hi>Lyon,</hi> and for no ground of Malverſation. But to theſe my Anſwers are plain. And to the Firſt, it is Anſwered, that the depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, being within a few Weeks before the pretended Act of Deforcement, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation happening to have been Intimat and publiſhed at the Mercat Croſs of <hi>Inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> where the Deforcement is alledged to have fallen out, there was not time nor pretence of <hi>Habit and Repute,</hi> which is inferred from length of time, and frequency of Acts. 2<hi>do.</hi> Tho <hi>Habite and Repute</hi> may ſerve the turn in Civil actione; yet it is not ſufficient to infer a Crime, or to be regarded, where the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is to be about <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> where things are to be <hi>Real</hi> and not <hi>Suſppoſed.</hi> 3<hi>tio.</hi> I did at the Bar give a new Libel to the Purſuers: And I do poſitively offer to prove, <hi>That</hi> Dallas <hi>his Deprivation was publickly known;</hi> which excludes all pretence of <hi>Habite</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>laſtly,</hi> the pretence, <hi>That he was deprived upon a light occaſion.</hi> I anſwer. whatever was the occaſion of his Deprivation, he was deprived, &amp; was no Meſſenger: And the Lyon Court who gave him his Office and Authority, has ſolemnly taken it away: And if he had believed himſelf leſed, he ought to have applyed to the <hi>Lords of Seſſion:</hi> But the truth is, he as Meſſenger having found Caution for his Office, and to perform cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain other Dueties conform to the Act of Parliament, under Condition to be depriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if he ſhould <hi>Faill,</hi> And having failled he was moſt juſtly <hi>deprived</hi> and his deprivation was fairly intimate by the <hi>Lyon Court:</hi> And therefore he was no Meſſenger; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently there could be no <hi>Deforcement.</hi> And the Purſuers are to blame, who uſed ſuch a Meſſenger after the legal form of Intimation.</p>
            <p>Nor is this all, though in my humble Opinion, this is very much. But further. it is evident, That the Execution of Deforcement in the eſſential parts of it, <hi>is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> And I muſt Beg leave to ſay, That however in Civil Caſes the Execution of a Meſſenger is <hi>probative;</hi> yet in Caſes inferring <hi>puniſhment,</hi> it is but conſidered as a <hi>naked aſſertion;</hi> unleſs it be aſtructed by the Depoſitions of the Witneſſes unſuſpect: Nor is it ſufficient to be Subſcribed by the Meſſenger in ſuch Caſes; becauſe even his Oath would be refuſed, in reſpect of the <hi>Perſonal</hi> Injury in the Lybel done to himſelf. And ſo it is, this Inſtrument is not only not aſtructed; but it is deſtroyed by the Teſtimonies. <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe the Teſtimonies differing from what they have Subſcrived under their hand, and each from another, do render both the Execution and themſelves ſuſpect: And your Lordſhips have found it in a Caſe perfectly paralel to this within this few days, betwixt the Earl of <hi>Tullibardine</hi> and <hi>Balnagoun.</hi> 2<hi>do.</hi> It was to have been proven the Blazon was diſplayed; that I was Wanded or Apprehended; and that it had been Intimat by whoſe Authority, and at whoſe Inſtance: Seeing it was ſo inſert in the Execution, and that ſome of theſe, eſpecially the <hi>Diſplaying the Blazon,</hi> as the differenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Badge of a Meſſenger from any other Leidge, and ſo an indiſpenſible ſolemnity; as <hi>McKenȝie</hi> in his Criminals <hi>pag.</hi> 259. And <hi>Stair.</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitut. pag.</hi> 725. <hi>Num.</hi> 14. <hi>and</hi> 738. <hi>N.</hi> 7. <hi>expreſly hold it as a principal.</hi> And <hi>Stair.</hi> ut ſupra <hi>pag.</hi> 730 hold it as a principal that an Exauctorat Meſſenger may be diſpiſed, if he cannot prove that he had Blazon diſplayed yet of this the Witneſſes prove nothing. Nay on the contrary, they De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone, they did not <hi>ſee the Blazon,</hi> They Depone they did not ſee me touched with the <hi>Wand</hi> an
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176122:2"/>
               <hi>of Peace;</hi> &amp; none of them did ſo much as hear <hi>Pitlivers</hi> Name mentioned. I deſire to know if they can produce the Teſtimony of any <hi>Lawyer,</hi> aſſerting, that a man without any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Mark or diſtinction by <hi>Blazon,</hi> or even a Meſſenger with his Blazon <hi>Diſplayed,</hi> without ſo much as a Warrand, or the Parties Name Intimat <hi>verbally,</hi> is a <hi>Legal</hi> Execution of a <hi>Caption:</hi> And without a legal Execution of a Caption. there can be no deforcement 3<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">tio.</hi>
               </hi> Though the Inſtrument bears other Witneſſes to have been preſent, beyond all manner of exception; yet the Purſuers has only adduced <hi>Bayn,</hi> deſigned <hi>Tullochs</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and a <hi>very Boy,</hi> who did not ſo much as ſign the Execution, untill the Meſſenger was <hi>Dead.</hi> And I offer to prove, That other of the Witneſſes being required to ſign the Execution, refuſed it; becauſe it was <hi>not true.</hi> So that it remains, Here is a Deforcement upon which I am fined in a very great Sum, whereupon my <hi>Eſcheat</hi> may fall without either <hi>Meſſengers</hi> or <hi>Execution.</hi> And it was no marvell though the Witneſſes ſhould <hi>Vary</hi> a little from themſelves and the Execution; becauſe I offer to prove. That the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution was filled up here in <hi>Edinhurgh,</hi> even after the Meſſenger was Dead: And I ſhall uſe no other Witneſſes then theſe already cited, or the Puſuers themſelves and their Agents: And I do contend, That an Execution ſo <hi>redargued,</hi> and ſent up <hi>blank</hi> is not to be conſidered as an Execution at all.</p>
            <p>I omit to tell your Lordſhips, I had no <hi>Acceſſion</hi> to the Acts of <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Deforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the Purſuers had only the Confidence to urge the Crime to have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted chiefly by my <hi>Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Riot,</hi> I deteſt and abhore it: It is neither ſuitable to the Character I have the Honour to bear, nor to my Breeding nor Temper. It is proven indeed, That Mr. <hi>William Baily,</hi> and other of the Defenders, were guilty of the Riot: But that I had any Acceſſion to it, I deſire the Purſuers frankly to ſay, what part of the Probation clears it. They did libel indeed, That <hi>Tulloch</hi> was carried to my Houſe, to my Cloſs, through a Town in Day-light, ignominiouſly; and there Beat. But they have not one ſingle Teſtimony to prove it; though the Carrying <hi>Tulloch</hi> thorow the Town in Day-light, might certainly have been proven, if it had <hi>been True.</hi> Nay, I poſitively offer to prove, That the Caſtle of <hi>Chanery,</hi> was not the ordinary place of my Reſidence; and that I was <hi>alibi</hi> all that Day.</p>
            <p>The Purſuers had not the Confidence to alledge, I was guilty <hi>directly.</hi> They did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed pretend to have the Matter cleared by their <hi>own Oath;</hi> which is <hi>New,</hi> in Matters <hi>Criminal.</hi> They did likeways alledge, That I ſhould be liable as an <hi>Highland Chief.</hi> But I humbly preſume, your Lordſhips did not proceed upon that Ground. Theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequential Hitts, do infinitly more concern the <hi>Nation,</hi> than <hi>me:</hi> It were above meaſure hard, that I, or Perſons in the like Circumſtances, ſhould be expoſed for the Riots of their Servants to pay ſuch <hi>great Sums,</hi> with <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> and other great <hi>Damnages;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when theſe Servants were never required, till they were out of my power, they having gone out of the Kingdom long before, and had no reſidence on my ground. This is not my Caſe alone, but is the Caſe of all Noblemen and Gentlemen in the <hi>Highland</hi> Countries; nay, and I may ſay, in the <hi>Nation:</hi> For there is a <hi>general</hi> Clauſe in the Act of Parliament founded on. But I am perſwaded your Lordſhips could not extend that Matter, tho the Purſuers were forced, through the ſtraitneſs of their Cauſe, to urge it.</p>
            <p>I am as fully perſwaded, That the <hi>Odious Miſrepreſentations</hi> againſt me, had no influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the Deciſion: And therefore I ſhall not trouble your Lordſhips with a long Vindication of my ſelf, as to my General Management and Conduct: I am perfectly ſatisfied your Lordſhips will proceed only on Probation, and the State of the Caſe, as is laid before you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it therefore pleaſe your Lordſhips to conſider theſe Principles of Law, and to find there is no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement <hi>proven:</hi> And that I had no Acceſſion to the<hi>Riot</hi> committed: And therefore to Aſſoilȝie me, and Liberate me from my Impriſonment.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>And your Petitioner ſhall ever Pray.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
